Stephen E. Malawista papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Organizations, Subseries 3
    - Arthritis Foundation, Connecticut Chapter, Board of Directors / Executive Committee, 1981, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Associates of Yale Medical Library, 1970-1980 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Association of American Physicians, 1976-1984 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Includes a nomination of Malawista for membership and published but confidential lists of nominees for membership, 1980-1983.
    - Association of American Physicians, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Additional materials on nominations for membership.
    - Association of American Physicians, 2000-2002 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Malawista's caustic response to the AAP requirement that members must attend a certain number of meetings.
    - Association of Professors of Medicine, 1979-1983 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Copy of a filled-out form on subspecialty fellowship training, and copy of a filled-out form on full-time faculty research.
    - Australian Rheumatism Association, 1981-1986 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Committee of a Thousand for Better Health Regulations, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Harvard College, Class of 1954, 1969-2000 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Heberden Society -- British Society for Rheumatology, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - International Inflammation Research Society, 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - International League Against Rheumatism (ILAR), 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      Folder includes meeting arrangements for ILAR '85 in Sydney, Australia at which Malawista was awarded the CIBA GEIGY ILAR Prize for Rheumatism. Malawista was an officer of ILAR. There is more information on the meeting in Series 9, Talks and Travel.
    - ILAR, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - ILAR, 1988-2001 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Interplanetary Society, 1966-1968, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Nobel Committee for Physiology or Medicine, 1976-1992 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Requests for nominations. There is no indication that Malawista responded.
    - PANLAR (Pan American League Against Rheumatism), 1982-1988 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Pan American Medical Association, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Physicians for Social Responsibility, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Malawista made a donation.
    - Revue Internationale de Rhumatologie, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Malawista became a member of the "Reading Committee" of this journal.
    - Saybrook College, Yale, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Sigma Xi, 1968-1980 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Societe Francaise de Rheumatologie, 1981-1983 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Ulysses S. Grant Foundation, 1967-1976 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      The Foundation, to which Malawista donated, sought "to help inner-city students help themselves by acting as a supplement to their regular New Haven school instruction." Most of the teachers were Yale students.
    - Yale Club of New York City, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Other, Subseries 4
    - "Crank Mail - To and From", 1970-1978 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      This was Malawista's own name for the contents of this folder. Malawista sometimes wrote protest letters about unfair fees or policies. Also included were what he likely considered "crank" theories in rheumatology.
    - Undeveloped Drug Project (Gerald Weissmann, NYU), 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Yale University: Administration, Teaching, Medical Practice, Sabbaticals, Series III
  - Yale appointments and personal folders on activities, Subseries 1
    - Appointments, Yale University School of Medicine, 1969-1975 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Activities, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      The folder heading is Malawista's. These folders contain materials that would help Malawista write his annual personal report to the Department of Internal Medicine. Folders include departmental correspondence.
    - Activities, 1982-1983 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Activities, 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Activities, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Personal annual report to Department of Internal Medicine, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital Survey of former residents, no date (Box 12, Folder 22)
      Copy of Malawista's responses to this survey and his critique of some of the questions. Survey asks for influences on his career choice.
    - Yale Patent Policy - Invention disclosure concerning cryopreservable cytoplasts, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 23)
      Malawista proposed to patent "Two types of cryopreservable cytoplasts from human polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMN) that maintain motile, phagocytic, and microbial function." He submitted an Invention Disclosure form to Yale but was informed by Robert Bickerton of the Office of Cooperative Research that the invention was not patentable "in its present stage of development."
    - Yale University Office of Cooperative Research concerning rights in Malawista's inventions, OCR142 and OCR791, 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 24)
      Malawista's further attempt to patent his invention (OCR 142) was declined by the Yale OCR and, at Malawista's request, the invention was released to him to patent and commercialize as he pleased, on condition that Yale received a portion of net income. The correspondence also concerns a second invention, "Antibody for the Detection of Gamma Related Proteins" (OCR791). Yale offered to release this invention to Malawista also.
  - Section of Rheumatology, Department of Internal Medicine, Subseries 2
    - Annual Reports of the Section of Rheumatology, 1974-1996
      These are annual reports of the Section of Rheumatology to the Department of Internal Medicine. For most of these reports, Malawista was serving as chief of the section. Early reports contain names of faculty, clinical staff, postdoctoral fellows, promotions, forthcoming appointments, terminations, current educational program, research in progress, and publications. Later reports became increasingly more elaborate and included clinical activity, program grants, educational activities, community activities, goals, and individual reports of each faculty member. The section grew under Malawista's leadership.
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1973-1974 - 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1978-1979 - 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1983-1984 - 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 7)
        Submitted by Dr. John A. Hardin.
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        Submitted by Dr. Joseph Craft.
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Annual Report of the Section of Rheumatology, 2003-2004 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Other Activities of the Section
      - Section of Rheumatology Journal Club, 1979-1984 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Rheumatology office renovations, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Rheumatology Residency Training Program, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 16)
        Documents required by the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education for Internal Medicine Subspecialty programs. They contain information on the teaching staff in Rheumatology at Yale.
      - Rheumatology Fellowship Program, 2003 July 1 (Box 13, Folder 17)
        Linda Bockenstedt, Fellowship Program Overview.
      - American-Soviet Exchange visit by Soviet rheumatologists, 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous section and department correspondence, 1964-2003 (Box 13, Folder 19)
        Materials grouped by archivist. Contains some material on faculty appointments.
      - Subspecialty form for Rheumatology Program, filled out by Malawista, after 1988 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Department of Internal Medicine activities
      - Department of Internal Medicine Research in Progress Meetings, 1977 Fall (Box 13, Folder 21)
        Contains schedule of presentations. Malawista was to speak on October 17 on "Microtubules and cyclic AMP in human leukocytes: On the order of things."
      - Department of Internal Medicine Retreat, New Haven Lawn Club, 1980 October 17-18 (Box 13, Folder 22)
        There is more information on departmental retreats in the folders that Malawista kept on annual activities.
      - Department of Internal Medicine Retreat, New Haven Lawn Club, 1984 January 28 (Box 13, Folder 23)
      - Review of the Department of Internal Medicine, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 24)
        The review was to take place February 23-24, 1982. Malawista was one of the faculty members scheduled to talk with one of the four outside reviewers.
  - Faculty committees, Subseries 3
    - Department of Internal Medicine, Committee on Incentives and Finances, 1973-1975 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Yale School of Medicine, General Clinical Research Unit Advisory Committee, 1976-1979 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Department of Internal Medicine, Clinical Faculty Appointments, 1982-1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Yale Policies and Procedures for Appointments, 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Senior Appointments Committee for the Biological Sciences, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Teaching, Subseries 4
    The main undergraduate medical course in which Malawista and the Section of Rheumatology taught was the Pathophysiology Course or Introduction to Clinical Medicine (ICM). Rheumatology was a module in the course. Folders may contain the schedule for lectures and workshops, materials Malawista used in teaching, correspondence, and student evaluations.
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1977 Spring (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Folder also contains the schedule of the Clinical Examination Course.
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1978 Spring (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1979 Spring (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Leo Cooney, Workshop on Examination of Joints, 1979 April 6 and April 27 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      This may have been part of the Pathophysiology course in 1979 taught by Leo Cooney and Malawista. It had workshops on this topic.
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1981 Spring (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1982 Spring (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Pathophysiology Course, 1983 Spring (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Pathophysiology ICM Course, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Introduction to Clinical Medicine, 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Plans for the rheumatology teaching in this course and 40 case studies (no patient names) that were likely used in teaching.
    - Introduction to Clinical Medicine, 1993 Spring (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Introduction to Clinical Medicine, 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Clinical Correlations Course, YSM 1, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Student evaluation for the Section's course, Rheumatology, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Workshops: "Mechanisms of Disease: Musculo-Skeletal/ Rheumatology Module", 2003-2004 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Physician Associate Program teaching, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Advances in Clinical Medicine, ACP Postgraduate Course, Yale, 1978 May 19 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      Malawista spoke on acute gouty arthritis.
    - Grand Rounds, "The Changing Basis for Acute Gouty Arthritis", 1991 October 17 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      Folder includes notes on Alfred Baring Garrod on gout (1876).
    - Grand Rounds at Yale, 1994-2007 (Box 14, Folder 23)
      Announcements for Grand Rounds, mostly for Rheumatology, but some for Internal Medicine and Pathology.
    - Teaching Slides, 1977, January 24 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Clinical teaching and patient care, Subseries 5
    - Rheumatology Consult Service schedules, 1974 -1988 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      A few memoranda, but mostly lists of who in Rheumatology was attending or on-call.
    - Rheumatology - Attending and clinics, 1990-1995 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Department of Internal Medicine Consulting Schedules, 1977-1983 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Yale-Affiliated Hospitals Postgraduate Program, 1976-1977 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      The affiliated hospitals in 1976-1977 were Bridgeport Hospital, Danbury Hospital, Greenwich Hospital, Griffin Hospital, Norwalk Hospital, St. Mary's Hospital, St. Vincent's Hospital, and Waterbury Hospital. Malawista and other Yale faculty visited these hospitals for clinical teaching of residents. These folders contain schedules and activities.
    - Yale-Affiliated Hospitals Postgraduate Program, 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Yale-Affiliated Hospitals Postgraduate Program, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Yale-Affiliated Hospitals Postgraduate Program, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Yale Affiliated Hospitals and Faculty Resource Program, 1999-2006 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Yale medical faculty visited affiliated hospitals for educational conferences. Folder contains a brochure on the program for 2000-2001 and schedules for the Section of Rheumatology.
    - Rheumatology Consult Service and Clinics at the Veteran's Administration (VA) Hospital, 1970-1983 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and lists concerning the consult service and clinics at the VA.
    - Arthritis/Rheumatology Clinics at the VA Hospital, 1986-1989 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Mostly correspondence concerning the operation of the clinics.
    - Evaluation of Malawista as attending physician, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Dana Incentive Program Physician Worksheet, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      This concerns finances for treating patients at the Dana Clinic, where Internal Medicine was then located. Malawista was under the target set for revenue generated.
    - Patient histories possibly used in clinical teaching (Restricted), 1989, 1991, no date (Box 15, Folder 13)
      Restricted because patients are identified by name and date. It is not clear that these were all written by Malawista.
  - Credentials for medical practice and hospital appointments, Subseries 6
    Includes certification for medical specialty practice and extensive forms that Malawista filled out periodically for renewal of hospital appointments at Yale-New Haven Hospital, the Veterans Administration Medical Center, and Gaylord Hospital.
    - Diplomate of the National Board of Medical Examiners (1959), 1964, June 2 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      Malawista passed the National Board of Medical Examiners examination in 1959. This card provides his certificate number, etc.
    - State of Connecticut medical license, 1973-2003 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - U.S. and Connecticut controlled substances registration certificates, 1973-2007 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      The Connecticut Department of Consumer Protection began to require annual controlled substance registration of practitioners in 1977. The federal certificates were issued by the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, later the Drug Enforcement Administration, of the Department of Justice. These date from 1973 to 2003.
    - American Board of Internal Medicine recertification, 1980-1998 (Box 15, Folder 17)
      Also includes directory entries sent to the American Board of Medical Specialists.
    - Continuing Medical Education (CME), 1990-2011 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and Yale-New Haven Hospital appointments, 1963-1989 (Box 15, Folder 19)
      In order to retain his appointment to the hospital staff, Malawista had to fill out increasingly extensive applications every two years.
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital appointments, 1992-2002 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital appointments, 2003, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital appointments, 2007, 2009, 2011 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital Staff IPA, Inc., 1999-2000 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Medical insurance for YNHH practitioners, 2000-2006 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Veterans Administration Hospital appointments, 1968-1981 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Gaylord Hospital appointments, 1968-1989 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Gaylord Hospital appointments, 1991-1999 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Gaylord Hospital appointments, 2000-2003 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Constitution Healthcare Plan, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Oxford Health Care credentialing, 1999-2001 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Anthem/Blue Cross Blue Shield credentialing, 1997, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - CIGNA credentialing, 2004-2005 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Sabbaticals from Yale, Subseries 7
    Malawista spent every sabbatical he was granted as well as triennial leaves in Paris collaborating with various French colleagues, especially Anne Chevance. These folders contain arrangements for his leaves from Yale and sometimes correspondence with Yale laboratory colleagues during his leave. Research notes from some of his sabbaticals can be found in Series 11.
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1973-1974, 1973 July (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Malawista spent his first sabbatical in 1971-1972 at the Centre de Genetique Moleculaire under Boris Ephrussi. This folder contains only a postcard from Paris announcing his return to New Haven (stamp removed prior to donation). More information might be found in Series 2, Correspondence, under Boris Ephrussi.
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1979-1980, preparation, 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      This sabbatical, the best documented, was spent at the Institut de Pathologie Cellulaire, Kremlin-Bicetre, under Marcel Bessis. The folder contains correspondence arranging for the sabbatical including Malawista's letter to Bessis asking to work in his laboratory.
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1979-1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      This folder contains primarily correspondence with the Rheumatology Section, especially with Wanda Prinz, section secretary, when Malawista was away in Paris. He sent her tapes to transcribe, and listed matters to take care of, and she forwarded correspondence sent to the Section. Various Yale matters were discussed.
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1979-1980: Paper presented by Malawista and report of the Institut de Pathologie Cellulaire for 1977-1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Malawista's paper was "L'Arthrite de Lyme: Un modele humain de la polyarthrite rhumatoide."
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1987-1988, 1985-1988 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Malawista spent this sabbatical at the Institut Pasteur. The folder contains mainly correspondence in preparation for his leave, and on his funding by a Fogarty International Center grant.
    - Travel to Paris, 1991 January 13-February 1, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      He planned to work at Institut Pasteur and the Hospital Salpetriere,
    - Short term travel requests to go to Paris, 1992-1993 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Sabbatical, Paris, 1994-1995 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      This sabbatical was spent at the Centre d'Ecologie Cellulaire, Hopital de la Salpetriere, working with Anne Chevance and others.
    - Travel to Paris, 1997 November 14-December 1 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Typed notes on his activities by day including laboratory notes and his and his wife's personal activities (meals, concerts, etc.)
    - Request for Triennial Leave of Absence to go to Paris, 2000 November 1 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Travel to Paris, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      Proposed research trip for three weeks. Folder contains correspondence with Jacques-Louis Binet, March 2003.
    - Request for Leave of Absence in 2005 to go to Paris, 2003 October 16 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Request for Leave of Absence in 2008 to go to Paris, 2006 October 25 (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Submission of manuscripts for publication, Series IV
  These files correspond with numbered entries in Malawista's Curriculum Vitae. See Box 1 for his CVs. His 2012 CV is also attached to this finding aid. Full citations have been copied and slightly rearranged from Malawista's CV. Early citations may not include end pages because Malawista and PubMed did not include them.
  Files may include correspondence with journal editors and coauthors, peer reviews of his submissions, Malawista's responses to reviews, comments of Yale faculty, drafts, notes, photographs, and diagrams. In many cases the initial submission was rejected or required revision. Often rejected manuscripts would be sent to one or more other journals. See also Subseries 3, "Manuscripts not published or not included in list of publications."
  - Manuscripts eventually published, Subseries 1
    - 1960s
      - Articles 4, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 1)
        Seegmiller, J.E., Howell, R.R. and Malawista, S.E. "The inflammatory reaction to sodium urate: its possible relationship to the genesis of acute gouty arthritis," J.A.M.A. l80: 469, l962.
        Correspondence with J. E. Seegmiller, 1962-1963 and a reprint of the article.
      - Articles 5, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        Zannoni, V.G., Jacoby, G.A., Jr., Malawista, S.E. and La Du, B.N. "The effect of folic acid on tyrosine metabolism in guinea pigs," J. Biol. Chem. 237:3506, l962.
      - Articles 7a, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 3)
        Malawista, S.E., and Seegmiller, J.E. "The inflammatory response to injected microcrystalline monosodium urate in man: The effect of pretreatment with colchicine," sent to the Journal of Clinical Investigation, but rejected on July 31, 1964.
        Includes correspondence, 1964, reviews, drafts, notes, photographs.
      - Articles 7b, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 4)
        Malawista, S.E. and Seegmiller, J.E. "The effect of pretreatment with colchicine on the inflammatory response to injected urate. A model for gouty inflammation," Ann. Int. Med. 62: 648, l965.
        Correspondence, 1964-1965, reviewer's report, drafts.
      - Articles 8, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 5)
        Malawista, S.E. "On the action of colchicine. The melanocyte model," J. Exp. Med. l22:36l-384, l965.
        Correspondence, 1965, drafts, notes, and a notice of the article in JAMA.
      - Articles 9, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 6)
        Malawista, S.E. "The action of colchicine in acute gout," in: Conference on Gout and Purine Metabolism, Princeton Inn, Princeton, NJ Oct. l964, A.B. Gutman, ed. Arthritis Rheum. 8, 752, l965.
        Correspondence, 1964-1965, materials on conference, drafts, notes, photographs.
      - Articles 10 (Restricted), 1965 (Box 18, Folder 7)
        Malawista, S.E., Seegmiller, J.E., Hathaway, B.E. and Sokoloff, L. "Sacroiliac gout," J.A.M.A. l94:954, l965.
        Correspondence, 1964-1966, drafts, patient records.
      - Articles 11, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 8)
        Malawista, S.E., Asterita, H. and Marsland, D. "Potentiation of the colchicine effect on frog melanocytes by high hydrostatic pressure," J. Cell Physiol. 68:13, l966.
        Correspondence, 1965-1966, review, comments by others at Yale, drafts, photographs, notes.
      - Articles 12a, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        Malawista, S.E. and Bodel, Phyllis T. "The dissociation by colchicine of phagocytosis from increased oxygen consumption in human leukocytes," rejected by the Journal of Experimental Medicine. The manuscript was then sent to the British Journal of Experimental Pathology which also rejected it.
        Folder contains correspondence, 1965-1966, and a copy of the paper.
      - Articles 12b, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        Malawista, S.E. and Bodel, Phyllis .T. "The dissociation by colchicine of phagocytosis from increased oxygen consumption in human leukocytes," J. Clin. Invest. 46[5]: 786-796, May l967.